Stan Drake Papers
Stan Drake Papers
1954-1971
1957-1967
Drake, Stan, 1921-
9 linear ft.
2,037 original daily and Sunday cartoons from the newspaper comic strip The Heart of Juliet Jones, clippings, correspondence and photographs.
148952
Biographical History
Stanley Drake (1921-1997), commonly known as Stan Drake, was an American cartoonist. He was co-creator of the newspaper comic strip The Heart of Juliet Jones.
Drake was born in Brooklyn and studied at the Art Students League of New York. His career began with work on comic books and pulp magazines such as Popular Detective and Popular Sports. He served in World War II and afterwards worked in advertising for a time. In 1953 he ventured into newspaper comics, collaborating with writer Elliot Caplin to create the long-running dramatic strip The Heart of Juliet Jones for King Features Syndicate. In 1989, Frank Bolle succeeded Drake on The Heart of Juliet Jones.
In 1984 Dean Young, who had taken over the comic strip Blondie when his father Chic Young died, invited Drake to join his team. Drake worked on Blondie until his death in 1997.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Stan Drake Papers consists primarily of original cartoons. There are 1,740 original daily cartoons, 297 original Sunday cartoons and 1 proof sheet (6 daily strips) from the newspaper story strip The Heart of Juliet Jones (1957-1963, 1965-1967). Daily cartoon: traces of graphite, blue pencil, opaque white, zipatone, pen and ink on illustration board (some on Craftint board), dimension vary approx. 6 x 20 in. to 5 ¾ x 22 ¾ in. Sunday cartoon: traces of graphite, opaque white, pasteovers, brush, pen and ink on illustration board, dimensions vary approx. 14 x 20 in. to 16 ¾ x 22 ½ in. Proof sheet: 8 ½ x 16 ½ on newsprint.
In addition to original cartoons, this collection also contains incoming correspondence from readers (1955-1971), a letter from French film director Alain Resnais (1965), photographs of Drake at various social functions (including photos of Mrs. Drake and family) (1954-1966), and newspaper and magazine clippings by and about Drake (1962-1966). Many of these items are accompanied by hand written explanatory notes from Drake.
A note on the story lines for The Heart of Juliet Jones: starting October 18, 1965, the daily and Sunday versions ran on a single continuity; previously, each ran separate stories.
Arrangement of the Collection
Daily and Sunday cartoons are arranged separately in chronological order. Other materials are foldered by type (with the Alain Resnais letter foldered separately).
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Caplin, Elliot.; Drake, Stan, 1921-; Resnais, Alain, 1922-2014.; Heart of Juliet Jones (comic strip); Art -- Cartoonists; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Comic books, strips, etc. -- United States.; Cartoons (humorous images); Clippings (information artifacts); Photographs.; Proofs (printed matter); Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Stan Drake, 1966-1971.
Inventory
- The Heart of Juliet Jones, 2,037
  Click here for detailed inventory.
  - Daily cartoons, 1,740
    - 1957 Jan - 1958 Jul (Box 1)
    - 1958 Aug - 1959 Jul (Box 2)
    - 1959 Aug - 1960 Jul (Box 3)
    - 1960 Aug - 1961 May (Box 4)
    - 1961 Jun - 1962 May (Box 5)
    - 1962 Jun - 1963 Jan (Box 6)
    - 1965 Jan - 1965 Sep (Box 7)
    - 1965 Oct - 1966 Sep (Box 8)
    - 1966 Oct - 1967 Aug (Box 9)
  - Sunday cartoons, 297
    - 1957 Jun - 1960 Dec (Oversize 1)
    - 1961 Apr - 1963 Dec (Oversize 2)
    - 1964 Jan - 1966 Jan (Oversize 3)
    - 1966 Jan - 1967 Jul (Oversize 4)
  - Proofs, 1
    - 24 Jan 1966 - 29 Jan 1966 (Oversize 1)
- Alain Resnais letter [in French], 1; film director Resnais, also head of French comics society, thanks Drake for loan of several original pieces sent for display in an international forum in Italy (includes hand written note from Drake)
  - 12 Feb 1965 (Box 10)
- Clippings, approximately 25; most with hand written explanatory notes by Drake
  - Al Capp interview from Playboy, (Dec 1965); 7 pages; in which Capp discusses Stan Drake; also includes clip of subsequent letter to the editor from Drake (Box 10)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1961-1966; clippings of Drake at various social events, including clips of Mrs. Drake and family (Box 10)
  - Tear sheet from comic strip Big Ben Bolt, 16 Feb 1961; Drake filled-in for John Cullen Murphy on this date using wife as model (includes hand written note from Drake) (Box 10)
- Correspondence, approximately 60 letters; incoming correspondence from readers, in chronological order
  - 1955-1971 (Box 10)
- Photographs, 6; photos of Drake at misc. public events; includes photo of Mrs. Drake modeling for Juliet Jones; hand written captions by Drake
  - 1954-1966, undated (Box 10)